"Where to Find Taurine and the Best Source"
Foods that contain
the highest levels of taurine
come from the sea,
particularly seaweed
and shellfish.
Here it is graphically,
so you can see how shellfish
compared to other meat.
The most concentrated source,
though, is dried nori,
the seaweed sheets
used to make sushi.
Land plants, however,
have negligible amounts.
So, a singular focus
on increasing dietary taurine
risks driving
poor nutritional choices,
because plant-rich diets
are associated with
human health and longevity.
I mean, energy drinks
have taurine too,
but slamming monster,
Red Bull, Rockstar, Cocaine
is probably not the best option.
The best choice
would probably be
to eat a healthy
plant-based diet
with supplemental taurine.
It’s such a simple molecule,
it can be
inexpensively synthesized.
So, you can just get
pure taurine powder.
Here’s how it all breaks down.
We can start with concentration.
Pure taurine
obviously has the most,
then dried nori,
then an average of clams,
oysters, mussels, and scallops,
then the average
across nine energy drinks,
then fin fish,
including the highest,
yellow sea bream,
down to tuna,
one of the lowest.
Then an average
of chicken, beef, and pork.
Nori’s looking pretty good
until you realize
how light it is.
To get one gram of taurine,
you’d have to eat
10 servings a day,
which is 40 sheets of nori,
which, even if
you could stomach it,
would exceed your recommended
iodine intake for the day.
The easiest way to get a gram
would be a quarter teaspoon
of pure taurine powder,
though one can of most
energy drinks would do it,
but then there’s the issue
of added sugars
or artificial sweeteners.
Two daily servings
of shellfish
is a lot of shellfish,
but certainly doable.
Easier than eating eight
daily servings of regular fish
or 18 servings a day
of land animals.
Here’s the cost comparison.
This is where
taurine powder really shines,
at as little as a penny per day
when bought in bulk,
it’s 50 times cheaper
than the next on the list.
Now, I used a combination
of canned and fresh shellfish
for this comparison.
If you just did,
like, canned clams,
it would be
more like $2.50 a day.
In terms of saturated fat
and cholesterol,
shellfish are extremely lean,
though the dietary guidelines
recommend that dietary
cholesterol consumption
be as low as possible,
90 is less
than half an egg yolk.
Allergies are an issue for some.
Shellfish is actually
the most common type
of food allergy
in the United States,
affecting about 1 in 35 people,
though it may
be as high as 1 in 10
depending on
the method of diagnosis.
Allergies to land-based meat
are rare,
unless you’ve been bitten
by certain types of ticks.
Foodborne illness
can also be a problem,
particularly since
shellfish, like oysters,
are sometimes eaten raw.
Usually,
it’s just gastroenteritis,
but it can sometimes develop
into serious infections.
Shellfish are filter-feeders,
so, they just pick up
and concentrate pathogens
from the environment.
Most outbreaks are actually
from human fecal pathogens
from sewage
that gets into the water,
or the overboard disposal
of feces from boats.
I guess I never really
thought about that,
but, like, most crews
from oyster-harvesting boats
were just, like, tossing
their waste overboard,
and it may come back
to bite them.
How common
is contamination of shellfish
with foodborne
human fecal viruses,
like norovirus,
the most common cause
of foodborne gastroenteritis?
Nearly one in three
samples of shellfish
carries this kind
of fecal contamination
that can make us sick,
yet, most consumers
ignore the fact
that shellfish
usually comes from places
polluted by
untreated human waste.
Though fecal contamination
is also found in 85 percent
of retail ground beef
and turkey,
about half of chicken,
and a third of pork.
Thankfully,
those meats are cooked,
but, still,
contaminated poultry products
probably cause the most
food poisoning deaths,
not shellfish.
Then, anytime you’re talking
about the aquatic food chain,
there are industrial pollutants.
Pollution of the oceans
is widespread and worsening,
and pollutants include
toxic heavy metals,
like mercury,
microplastics,
and industrial toxins,
like PCBs.
Yes, we’ve been eating shellfish
for more than
a hundred thousand years,
but that was before
we so polluted our waterways.
Shellfish pump and filter
such large quantities of water
in their feeding processes
that they just tend
to accumulate
a lot of contaminants,
like heavy metals.
So, the consumption
of contaminated shellfish
can lead to neurological
and developmental defects,
reproductive and
gastrointestinal disorders,
and in extreme cases, death.
That does seem a little extreme.
They’re talking
about contamination
with algal toxins.
While filter-feeding,
shellfish
can ingest toxic algae,
which can produce a hundred
different natural toxins.
So, the shellfish
can accumulate these toxins
and pass them on to consumers.
So, although we refer to them
as shellfish toxins,
they’re actually no more
from the shellfish themselves
than the human
fecal viruses were.
When humans
ingest different toxins
accumulated in seafood,
they may exhibit
different poisoning syndromes.
There’s paralytic
shellfish poisoning,
amnesic shellfish poisoning,
neurotoxic shellfish poisoning,
and diarrhetic
shellfish poisoning.
Symptoms-wise,
these can include
abdominal pain, vomiting,
diarrhea, severe headaches,
confusion, agitation,
sleepiness, memory loss,
coma, loss of coordination,
excessive scratching, tremors,
heart arrhythmias, seizures,
lethargy, inappetence,
I’d never heard that word
for loss of appetite,
blindness, muscular twitches,
behavioral changes,
convulsions,
and death,
sometimes within hours.
No antidotes are available.
Sometimes,
neuropsychological symptoms
can last for years.
Some of the toxins
may be carcinogenic,
linked to a variety
of different cancers.
This may help explain
cohort studies
that found associations
between colorectal cancer
and the consumption
of shellfish and shrimp.
But, of course,
it could also be
the industrial pollutants.
The bad news is
that toxic algae blooms
are getting worse,
thanks to climate change.
But the good news is that
the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration
has established
a surveillance program
to test for toxins.
So, there are regulatory limits.
Unfortunately, despite
strong regulatory limits
protecting people
from acute poisoning,
there is a growing
body of evidence
suggesting there are
significant health consequences
following repeated exposures
to levels
of an amnesic neurotoxin
known as domoic acid,
even when below
current safety guidelines.
Those in the Pacific Northwest
who eat a lot
of razor clams, for example,
with presumed safe levels,
were found to be at risk
for clinically significant
memory problems.
They are five to six times
more likely to have problems
with everyday memory,
like, having to check whether
you actually did something,
or forgetting to tell
someone something important,
or being forgetful day to day.
The toxin doesn’t seem
to be affected by cooking,
and the "very high"
levels of consumption
were just more than
15 clams a month.
So, Washington State
tells its residents
to eat less than that,
but to reach
a gram a day of taurine
you’d have to eat 10 a day,
300 a month.
The bottom line is that
even at levels deemed "safe"
under current regulatory limits,
algal toxins
may not make mollusks
the best source
for taurine supplementation.